<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Bridgwater at an ordination of ministers, August 2. 1698. By J.B. Published at the request of some of the hearers.</title>
            <author>J. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B123A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133594</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133594)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2433:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Bridgwater at an ordination of ministers, August 2. 1698. By J.B. Published at the request of some of the hearers.</title>
                  <author>J. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Roberts, and are to be sold by him at his shop in Bridgwater; and by John Sprint in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Wing B123A which has '1698' in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing B123A, reel 2433, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133594:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at BRIDGWATER, AT AN Ordination of Miniſters, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 2. 1698.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of ſome of the Hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Roberts,</hi> and are to be Sold by him at his Shop in <hi>Bridgwater;</hi> and by <hi>John Sprint</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:133594:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:133594:2"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JER. XXIII. 21, 22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But if they had ſtood in my Counſel, and had cauſed my People to hear my words, then they ſhould have turned them from their evil ways, and from the evil of their doings.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> lived in the declining time of the Kingdom of <hi>Judah;</hi> in which (as he complains) Profaneneſs was gone forth into all the Land. For the reforming of which, he was raiſed up, but not prevailing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he doth foretell the Captivity, which was now at hand. Hereby it appears what critical Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances the Prophet was in; for it was hard to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that what he had foretold would come to paſs, was not what he deſir'd ſhould come to paſs. This put him upon that ſolemn appeal to God, <hi>I have not deſir'd the wofull day, O Lord thou know'ſt.</hi> It did perhaps make the People ſuſpect him to be a man diſaffected to the Government, that he differ'd in a manner from all men as to the intereſt of the Nation as things then ſtood; for he all along told them, that it was their only way to preſerve themſelves from utter Deſtruction, to ſubmit to the <hi>Babylonians</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and not to depend upon the vain Succors of <hi>Egypt,</hi> this would prove a broken Reed, <hi>Egypt</hi> was then declining, and perhaps they had it ſtill in thier remembrance, that <hi>Joſiah</hi> by taking part with <hi>Aſſinia</hi> againſt <hi>Pharaoh</hi> at <hi>Megiddo,</hi> did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſe his life, but gave ſuch a blow to the Kingdom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133594:3"/>
of <hi>Judah,</hi> that it did never after that time recover it ſelf, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 23.29. It ſeems, that the meaſures which wiſe Princes ſhould take for their own ſafety muſt change with the Times. For that which at one time may preſerve, upon the change of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, may undo a Kingdom. Now this Counſel of the Prophet not to depend upon <hi>Egypt</hi> diſpleaſed the Court, but it did much more provoke them, that the Prophet did ſo plainly and particularly tell them of thoſe Sins that provok'd God againſt the Nation. All men, but chiefly great men, above all others, Courtiers are impatient of Reproof, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord that doth not gently handle them, muſt needs fall under their Diſpleaſure; for they that go in ſoft Raiment, and are in Kings houſes do expect to be complemented as well in the Pulpit as in the Street. It is no marvel if the Prophet in theſe hard circumſtances was uneaſie; for he had King and Court, City and Country, Prieſts, Prophets and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt him, as one that had deceived the People, as one diſaffected to the Government; hence are his Complaints, <hi>cap.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Wo is me that my mother brought me forth as a man of Contention to the whole earth.</hi> He had neither lent nor borrowed upon Uſury, yet every one hated him, every one was againſt him. But that which above any thing gave him trouble, was the falſe Prophets, that told Prince and People the contrary to what <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied. Theſe were they that cried Peace, that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perſuade the people that no evil was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>Hearken not the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that propheſie unto you; they make you vain, they ſpeak a Viſion of their own hearts, and not out of the mouth of the Lord</hi> And what was it that theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets would have the People believe? why, that no evil was coming upon them, there was no need of a Reformation, all would end well, and in this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133594:3"/>
they expreſs great confidence, and pretended Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Who hath ſtood in the Counſel of the Lord, and hath perceived and heard his word?</hi> i. e. who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our ſelves, who better than we are acquainted with the ſecret purpoſes of God to this Nation? And therefore believe not <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> he is a perſon diſaffected to the Government, and ſpeaks his own diſcontent, and not what ſhall come to paſs. <hi>Egypt</hi> will relieve us, and ſave us out of the hands of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Babylonians;</hi> we ſhall have Peace, there will be no Captivity. Now theſe Prophets did not only deceive the people, but they did alſo ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the hands of evil Doers. So that none did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from his Wickedneſs, <hi>Profaneneſs was gone forth into the whole land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now concerning theſe Prophets, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in theſe words doth obſerve two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. How they made themſelves Prophets, but God had not ſent them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How they had abuſed the people and deceived them, ſpeaking as from God what God had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd unto them. <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſied. They thruſt themſelves into the Miniſtry, and ran with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their errand.</hi> And 'tis for this that they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely rebuk'd.</p>
            <p>So that from the words I may obſerve how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it is for thoſe that come in God's Name, that they be ſent of God, for to go before we are ſent, to propheſie before God ſpeak to us, is to do what theſe falſe Prophets did, who fail'd in theſe two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In entring into their Office, being not call'd to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the execution of their Office, for they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied to the people, but it was not what God had ſpoken to them; for they told the people there was no evil coming upon them, no Captivity at hand, all would end well; <hi>Egypt</hi> with its Succors would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133594:4"/>
be able to preſerve them from the growing greatneſs of the <hi>Babylonians</hi> and <hi>Caldeans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, that I find my ſelf under one diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which I did not conſider, when I firſt applied my ſelf to ſpeak to theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> that in ſpeaking to them I muſt apply what is ſpoken of Prophets ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and immediately called and ſent to that which is ordinary, for ſo is the calling of a Miniſter, for I will not meddle with thoſe that pretend to be immediately called and ſent of God. However, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing for what is extraordinary, and the words may be fitly enough applied to a Goſpel-Miniſter. We muſt be ſent, as well as thoſe Prophets that were immediately ſent; tho' I confeſs, 'tis not in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects as they were ſent. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>How ſhall they preach, except they be ſent?</hi> Who can in the name of God declare the word of Reconciliation as the Meſſenger of God, that is not authoriſed and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſo to do? and yet it is not the meaning of the Apoſtle that every Miniſter muſt be ſent as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>I have received of the Lord, that which I have alſo delivered unto you.</hi> We do not pretend that we have received either our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or our Errand immediately from Chriſt, as the Apoſtle did, and yet a Miniſter that preacheth the ſame Doctrine, may without preſumption ſpeak the ſame words. Something the Miniſter receives, which he is not to deliver: the Officer may, and in ſome caſes ought to ſhew his Warrant that gives him Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but not to part with it. However as a Miniſter is to take heed, that he don't deliver what he hath not received; ſo alſo he muſt not pretend to come in God's name, except God hath ſent him. He that is not ſent, hath no Authority to make uſe of that man's Name that did not ſend him.</p>
            <p>This I confeſs, may be a ſuitable Subject upon this occaſion, to ſhew how neceſſary 'tis for Miniſters to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133594:4"/>
be ſent of God, in order to our Acceptance with God, and Succeſs among the people, that the want thereof may not lie at our own doors. As it was with theſe falſe Prophets, <hi>If they had ſtood in my Counſel, and cauſed my people to hear my words, then they ſhould have turn'd them from their evil way, and from the evil of their doings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe it is agreed upon on both hands, that they that preach the Goſpel muſt be ſent; and the difference is chiefly in this, how they muſt be ſent, who are they that under God muſt inveſt them in the Miniſtry; I ſay, for this reaſon I ſhall wave the uſual method of a Sermon, and ſpend the remainder of our time in ſpeaking to this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How may it be known to the ſatisfaction of our ſelves, and the people that attend our Miniſtry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are ſent of God? I mean, as far as 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for thoſe that pretend not to be immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called and ſent of God. We all love glad Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and are apt to wellcome the Meſſenger that brings them, and indeed it is but fit it ſhould be ſo. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.7. <hi>How beautifull are the feet of them that bring glad tydings?</hi> And yet 'tis not fit that every one that knows (as <hi>Ahimaz</hi>) ſomething of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſhould go without ſending. Our Brethren that ſatisfie themſelves in their Conformity are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that the publick Maintenance is engroſſed to themſelves, but they would engroſs the Miniſtry, many of them; and don't only condemn us for the exerciſe of our Miniſtry as Schiſmatical, but they would have it believ'd among the people, that our Miniſtry is a Nullity, that we are not ſent of God. Now to relieve our ſelves againſt this Cenſure, and to give what ſatisfaction I can; I ſhall make it my buſineſs at this time to anſwer this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> How ſhall it appear that we are ſent of God? <hi>No man taketh</hi> (ought to take) <hi>this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God,</hi> Heb. 5.4.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:133594:5"/>Now in anſwer to this Queſtion, I ſhall lay down theſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He that is duely ſent of God doth ſincerely deſign, and chiefly deſire the Glory of God, and the good of Souls, by turning men from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Satan to God. The deſign of the Miniſtry is to better Mankind; and for this end St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Miniſter ſent of God is competently qualified for that Service, with the Gifts of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Utterance, both which are eſſentially ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To make him a Miniſter, he muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, devoted, conſecrated and ordained by ſuch as have received power to inveſt men in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. He that hath theſe Qualifications, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere deſire to ſerve God in the Miniſtry, is qualified for it, not only in his own conceit, but in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe to whom it belongs to ordain, and is by them ſet apart for the work; the People ought to own him as a Miniſter, as one whom God hath ſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We can never juſtifie our ſelves before God, no, nor to our own Conſciences, except there be a ſincere deſire to do good to mens Souls, except we can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I ſeek not yours but you, your good more than your reward.</hi> For to deſign the Miniſtry as a Calling to live by, and to look no high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is ſo low and mean, that he that looks no higher is unworthy of the Name. True it is, that he <hi>that preacheth the Goſpel muſt live by the Goſpel, as they that ſerve at the Altar had their maintenance from the Altar,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.13, 14 For if it be a Calling, and if Miniſters ought as much as they are able to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the work of their Miniſtry, as their Calling, and that wholly, as the Apoſtle commandeth <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to do, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14, 15. <hi>Give Attendance to read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to exhortation, to doctrine, neglect not the gift that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133594:5"/>
is in thee, which was given thee by Propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery. Meditate upon theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them.</hi> I ſay, if it be a Calling, 'tis almoſt as eaſie to prove that a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is due to them, as 'tis to prove that they muſt eat and drink: and the people are to conſider this more than (I fear) they do. The want hereof muſt in time quite extinguiſh, or at leaſt cauſe the Miniſtry to dwindle away into Contempt. And the Lamp muſt needs go out, when 'tis not maintain'd with Oil, though not ſo ſoon as when 'tis blown out. People therefore ſhould take heed that they do not that by detaining a maintenance, which their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would do by force and violence. And yet to deſign the Miniſtry as a Calling to live by, and to have no higher ends is baſe and mercenary.</p>
            <p>The firſt Queſtion in the Office of Ordination is this, <hi>viz.</hi> Do you truſt that you are inwardly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Ghoſt to take upon you this Office and Miniſtry to ſerve God, for the promoting of his Glory, and for the edifying his People? And the anſwer that every one muſt make that will be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd is this, <hi>viz.</hi> I truſt I am. Surely the thing is to be conſider'd by all Miniſters, by us that are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that if our deſign was not entirely the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God and the good of Souls, to be aſham'd of it, and humbled for it that we came under that Curſe that was threatned againſt the houſe of <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.36. <hi>Put me into one of the Prieſts Offices that I may eat bread.</hi> And thoſe that at this time are entring upon the Miniſtry ſhould ſeriouſly conſider that Queſtion, whether they can with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence make that anſwer, and not lie in the Preſence of God, and the Congregation in ſo ſolemn a manner, and upon ſo ſolemn an occaſion. And yet 'tis too evident that many Miniſters never had that inward motion nay perhaps did never conſider what it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133594:6"/>
is. If it were well weigh'd, that heat that they have to be made Miniſters would ſoon abate in them, that have nothing more in their Eye, but ſome Benefice, to which they cannot have Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Induction, but by Orders. And ſo they enter into the Miniſtry as men do into ſecular Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and Callings to get a livelihood. Now if men do make their firſt ſtep into the Miniſtry by a Lie, ſuch an open ſolemn Lie as this, that they are mov'd by the Holy Ghoſt to take upon them this Miniſtry; to ſerve God in the edifying his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and yet as to this inward motion they know nothing of it but this, that they know they never had it. It is no great wonder if ſuch Miniſters ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten into the Miniſtry as into a Calling to maintain and enrich themſelves, doe endeavour to make the beſt of their Calling, by graſping into their hands as many places as by Favour or Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they can get, and then ſubſtitute ſome poor illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Curate, a thing ſo openly ſcandalous, that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> would have reform'd it in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> nay it is reform'd in ſome Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches belonging to that Communion, but not in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> notwithſtanding the great out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries we have made about our Separation from them. I ſay the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> would have reform'd it, had it been over-rul'd by the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> The preſent King by his Injunctions to the Biſhops doth enough ſhew his diſlike of this matter, if they to whom it belongs to prevent it will do their part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Miniſter that is ſent of God muſt be qualified with thoſe Gifts of Knowledge and Utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as are highly neceſſary to the Miniſtry. Tho' 'tis hard to determine what degrees of Gifts are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, yet 'tis eaſie to ſee that degrees of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge are neceſſary to him that is to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct men above what is neceſſary to others. The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133594:6"/>
Maſter ſhould know more than the Scholar, the Guide ſhould know the way better than the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller that takes him for his Guide. Tho' the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would keep the people in ignorance, they are for a learned Clergy. God doth make ſo great uſe of the gifts of Miniſters, that 'tis ſtrange that any that pretend to Learning ſhould make light of the Qualifications of Miniſters, under a pretence that the Office ſuffereth, and that people ſhould not much concern themſelves about the gifts of their Miniſters, God (they ſay) having inſtituted the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice will bleſs it, and is not tied to the gifts of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. True it is that God is not tied to means and inſtruments; he can do his own work without means, and by weak inſtruments. But yet this is no rule to us, for we are not to conſider what God can do, nor what he hath done when means have fail'd, when upon the Nations coming out of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery able Miniſters were not to be had; I don't doubt but that good was done by ſuch as could be had. Some could do no more than read. But we are to conſider what is the moſt likely way, in which we may expect the Concurrence of God's Grace and Bleſſing in the uſe of means. Whether it is not more likely that God may bleſs a laborious, faithfull, holy Miniſtry, than an ignorant, idle, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one. Except in extraordinary Caſes, God doth uſe means adapted for the work he employs them about, and ſurely a Miniſter that takes no care of his own Soul, is not like to ſave other mens. <hi>Moſes</hi> was raiſed up of God to bring the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt. Moſes</hi> was in every thing fitted for that work except in a readineſs of Speech, which was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd by <hi>Aaron,</hi> who was to be his Spokeſman. <hi>Moſes</hi> was bred up at Court, and train'd up in the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> a man that underſtood the rules of Policy, and the meekeſt man upon earth.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133594:7"/>
One that was for forty years an Herdſman, and had travers'd that Wilderneſs through which he was to lead the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Whatever St. <hi>Paul</hi> was before his Converſion, God that put him into the Miniſtry made him an able Miniſter; and tho' our Saviour choſe for his Diſciples unlearned Fiſhermen, yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to look well to the Gifts and Abilities of ſuch as he ſhould take into the Miniſtry, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>The ſame commit thou to faithfull men, who ſhall be able to teach others, and to lay hands ſuddenly on no man,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22. Is it not evident, that 'tis not the Office but the Gifts of Miniſters and their diligence and induſtry that muſt convert and edifie the people? What is the Miniſtry, but an Office ordain'd for inſtructing the people? And what is the Office but an obligation to do the work of the Office? and is the work done by an obligation upon men to do it? Doth the Office of a Conſtable, or the Mayor of the Town prevent and puniſh Debauchery and Profaneneſs, or the care and diligence of him that is in the Office? Is a ſick man heal'd by the Office, or rather is he not heal'd by the skill of the Phyſician? Why ſhould the Kingdom be at that charge to give a liberal Maintenance to the Miniſtry, if there be little odds as to the Gifts and Abilities of Miniſters? Gifts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of knowledge and utterance are highly neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him that would prove himſelf to be ſent of God. <hi>The Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and they</hi> (the people) <hi>ſhould ſeek the law at his mouth, for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 2. And the qualifications of a Miniſter ſhould conſiſt in theſe two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Miniſters ſhould be able to ſpeak from the people to God, to open the caſe of the people, their wants and deſires, and his own wants and deſires in Prayer. Miniſters ſhould be able to do this in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133594:7"/>
orderly, clear, and congruous Expreſſions, according to the ſeveral occaſions that will happen, which a ſtint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed form can never comprehend. And that a ſtinted form cannot comprehend the ſeveral occaſions for which Prayers and Praiſes ought to be offer'd up to God appears from hence, that as oft as days of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and Thankſgiving are commanded to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, Prayers are compoſed and ſent down to be uſed for that occaſion, which is an open acknowledgment that there is a Defect in our Liturgy, and that 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſupply that Defect. But what proviſion is there made for the particular occaſions of each Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and for the ſeveral Members of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation? If new Prayers are neceſſary for days of Humiliation and Thankſgiving, why not for ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular occaſions of the Congregation? The Miniſter had need to be able to do this, for a ſtinted Form can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend the various Accidents of Life, for which Prayers and Praiſes are to be made. There will be inconveniences that may attend conceiv'd Prayer; and are there none on the other hand, that will attend compoſed Forms? Every thing that is the work of man, will ſavour of the imperfection of man. However, we are (as I think) on the ſureſt ſide, for the Scripture commands us to pray; but what place of Scripture commands that Prayer muſt be always as oft as the Church comes together in the ſame words? If a ſtint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Form were ſo neceſſary as is pretended, I don't think it would have been left undetermined in the Scripture; neither would the Apoſtles have left the ſeveral Churches that they planted, unprovided of a Form of Prayer, if a Form had been neceſſary. This Argument which ſome have well improv'd, carries that weight with it, that they that are for the impoſing of Forms, do yet acknowledge that ſuch Forms of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from which it was not lawfull for the Miniſter to vary, were not impoſed for the firſt three Centuries; and conſequently that they came not into the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133594:8"/>
Church till about four or five hundred years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt. Now to take off this prejudice, they tell us that then there was no need of them, Miniſters were ſupplied with extraordinary Gifts, Gifts of Tongues, Gifts of Miracles, Gifts of Propheſie. I confeſs, 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evident that ſuch extraordinary Gifts were then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed; but that every one that was ordain'd to the Miniſtry, had thereupon a conſtant extraordinary Gift either for Prayer or Preaching, is ſooner ſaid than prov'd. Nay rather the contrary to this is evident, that tho' the firſt general Preachers of the Goſpel that were not limited to this or that Church, but were to ſpread the Goſpel in all Places and Nations; tho' I ſay theſe (no doubt) had ſuch an extraordinay Gift, it doth not appear that all others had it. The directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> about the Qualifications of Miniſters do plainly intimate the contrary. So that ſtinted Forms of Prayer coming into the Church not till four or five hundred years after Chriſt; whether the impoſing of Forms of Prayer be to be juſtified from hence, becauſe about 500 years after Chriſt, they were impos'd; I ſay, whether this be a good argument muſt be determined from the ſtate of the Church at that time. As to this all that I ſhall ſay is to repeat the words of one that hath ranſacked all the Corners, penetrated the inwards, and dived to the bottom of Antiquity, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Clerkſon,</hi> p. 181. ſpeaking of the Introduction of Liturgies. They were not entertained, till nothing was admitted into the Church, <hi>de novo,</hi> but corruptions, or the Iſſues of them; no change made in the ancient Uſages, but for the worſe, no Notions from its Primitive State, but down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards into degeneracy, till ſuch orders took place as reſpected, not what was moſt agreeable to the rule and primitive Uſage, or what was beſt to uphold the life and power of Religion in its ſolemn Exerciſes, or what might ſecure it from that dead Heartleſneſs and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133594:8"/>
into which Chriſtianity was ſinking. In a word, not till the Church was rather to be pitied than imitated. Thus far Mr. <hi>Clerkſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, however, 'tis a cunning Device, for by this means, <hi>viz.</hi> the caſting out of all Prayer but what is read out of a Book, there will be no diſcernable dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Miniſters Gifts; but they will hardly be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prevent the people from ſaying, this way of Pryer is no more than we our ſelves can do, why ſhould we maintain and honour men for doing no more than a Boy of ten or twelve years old can do? nay there will be a greater inconvenience than this; Let Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters be provided for with Forms of Prayer made to their hands, without putting forth themſelves to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the Gift of Prayer, and in time they will be una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pray otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Miniſter ſhould be able to ſpeak from God to the people; to declare the whole Will and Counſel of God to them. The Work and Deſign of the Miniſtry is to better Mankind, to turn men from their evil ways, and from the evil of their doings; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a work doth require Gifts of Knowledge and Utterance. Converſion doth reſtore man to the image of God, which conſiſts in Knowledge, Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs, and the means muſt be fitted to the end. Miniſters ſhould be able not only to make Sermons, ſet ſtudied Diſcourſes, but upon all occaſions to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon. I am ſure this is that which Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters promiſe to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to uſe both publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Monitions and Exhortations as well to the ſick as to the whole: <hi>Sponſ.</hi> 3. Office of Ordination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Together with theſe, there ought to be the approbation of thoſe to whom it belongs to judge of the Qualifications of thoſe that would devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Labours to God in the Service of the Miniſtry, when theſe have approv'd them as perſons duly qualified, and commended them to God, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133594:9"/>
have by Prayer and Impoſition of hands inveſted them in the Miniſtry, theſe are to be owned by the people as Miniſters ſent of God.</p>
            <p>I know that ſome engroſs this power of making Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to ſuch as are now called Dioceſan Biſhops, whom they make ſo neceſſary to Ordination of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that whoever is ordain'd without them by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of particular Congregations, ſome of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are pleas'd to ſay, theſe Ordinations having not the concurrence of a Dioceſan Biſhop, are a mere nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. And the Parliament that made the Law, that required Reordination of all ſuch as had been thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, were no doubt of this opinion. Some indeed have ſaid their Ordination was required to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Miniſtry, and not the Office. A Licenſe would have done that without Ordination. Moreover there was no difference made betwixt thoſe that had been ordain'd before, and thoſe that pretended not to it; which proves that our Law-makers, of whom the Biſhops were a part, look'd upon all thoſe Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as a Nullity, for no leſs was required of us that had been ordain'd than of thoſe that had not been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd. And yet they would not declare that all our Miniſtration were a nullity. So inconſiſtent are all they with themſelves that deſign the intereſt of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, more than of the truth. This puts me in mind of what a reverend Miniſter then told one of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; <hi>viz.</hi> I am afraid (ſaid he) there is that Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhewn in the Act of Conformity, that 'tis to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very many Miniſters will not conform: To whom the Biſhop replied, I am afraid there will be too many. Surely (to ſpeak modeſtly) that Prelate was not of the opinion of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who rejoyced that Chriſt was preached, tho' ſome that preached him were no great friends to the Apoſtle. But in confirmation of what I have to ſay, I would not make Reflections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what is paſt any further than our own Vindication will make it neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:133594:9"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Therefore to prove this, let it be ſuppoſed that a Miniſter of a particular Congregation (whom for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction-ſake we call a Presbyter) be of an inferior or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a Biſhop. It is upon this pretence that the power of Ordination is denied to them. Now if theſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (Presbyters) being but the Miniſters of particular Congregations may make a Biſhop, they may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make and ordain Miniſters; for if they can do the greater, they may do the leſs. This was the anſwer of Archbiſhop <hi>Uſher</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who told that King, that in the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters always made their own Biſhop. And the thing is ſo neceſſary, that Epiſcopacy can't well be preſerv'd, except the inferiour Clergy have a power to make their own Biſhops. Suppoſe as ſometimes it hath fallen out here in this Kingdom, that there were not Biſhops enough to conſecrate Biſhops, who can make them but the inferiour Clergy? It fell out ſo in <hi>England</hi> at the coming of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to the Crown. Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> died within four and twenty hours of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and upon his death the See of <hi>Canterbury</hi> being void, Dr. <hi>Parker</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to it, there were not (as Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> obſerves) Biſhops enough of the Proteſtant Religion to ordain him, and the Popiſh Biſhops would not: ſo he was made Biſhop by <hi>Barlow, Story, Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> and <hi>Hodgkins,</hi> three of theſe were only Titular, and had no Sees, and the other a Suffragan. So that the firſt Biſhop that was made here upon the coming of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to the Crown, was made by Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and not by Dioceſan Biſhops. This put Mr. <hi>Maſon</hi> upon the writing of his Book in Vindication of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miniſtry againſt the Papiſts, who triumph'd much upon this occaſion. Surely therefore, if Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may make Biſhops, who pretend to be a ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our order to them, what ſhould hinder that they ſhould not have a power to ordain Miniſters? Juſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133594:10"/>
ſuch another abſurdity the Papiſts run themſelves into; for they alſo appropriate the power of Ordination to Dioceſan Biſhops, and yet according to the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, every Prieſt by a few words ſpeaking can make a God, and turn the Elements of Bread and Wine into the natural Body of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but they muſt not preſume to make Miniſters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The nature of Ordination proves our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry to be no Nullity. Ordination is but a determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the perſons to be ordained, as perſons duly qualified for the Office, whereupon they are by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Impoſition of hands inveſted in the Miniſtry. Now what is there in this, that Miniſters may not do without a Dioceſan? We do not give them their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and miniſterial Authority, that is from God, and what that power is that God gives them, 'tis not we, but the word of God that muſt determine. The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority Ecceſiaſtical or Miniſterial is from God as the civil power. Now 'tis not uſual for Kings to be inveſted by Kings, 'tis always done by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. True it is in the Office of Ordination as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Biſhop is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to ſay, Take thou Authority to preach the word of God, and to miniſter the holy Sacraments. But 'tis not the Biſhop that is the Donor of that Authority, and that 'tis not ſo, will appear to him that doth but conſider this one thing, they that ordain men to the Office, don't make the Office. He only gives the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that made the Office to which the power belongs. As the King that can make Corporations and Mayors, doth give them what power they have. Our Brethren that would nullifie our Miniſtry, are pleas'd to tell us, that Biſhops in ordaining Miniſters do give them what power they have, and that Miniſters can have no more power than the Biſhops intended to give them in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and that therefore Presbyters can have no power to ordain, becauſe the Biſhops in ordaining
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133594:10"/>
them, intended it not to them. True it is that about two hundred years ago all our Ordinations came from thoſe that were of the Epiſcopal Perſwaſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; and who can pretend that they that then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd did intend to give this power? The argument were of weight, if the Biſhops had made the Office, but it being not ſo, it matters not what their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were that then ordain'd Miniſters. Were it not ſo, what I pray would become of the Reformation? Had our Reformers no more power than the Pope and his Biſhops intended to give them? Surely they never intended them a power to reform. Ordination therefore being but a determining of the Perſons, and an inveſting men in the Miniſtry, what power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Miniſters have, is from God: as when one of your Neighbours is made Mayor of your Town, he doth not receive his power from them that choſe him, nor from him that ſwears him, but from the King, that gave the Charter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I would argue from the neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of that opinion that would engroſs the power of Ordination to a Dioceſan, and make all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations a meer Nullity. It followeth (and they own it) that their Miniſtry is no Miniſtry, their Sacraments no Sacraments, their Churches no Churches, and 'tis well if they allow them to be in a ſtate of Salvation: and yet theſe very men acknowledge that they are true Miniſters and Churches, that have <hi>Roman</hi> Ordination, proclaiming hereby an utter Renunciation of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, which have no ſuch Ordinations, and yet a Coalition with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, whom they will allow (if any of them will come over to us) the exerciſe of their Miniſtry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ordination, but not the Proteſtant Miniſters that were driven out of <hi>France.</hi> That I do not wrong them, ſee Mr. <hi>Dodwell</hi>'s Preface to the Unity of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, <hi>p.</hi> 11. where he ſaith, That we are guilty of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betting
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133594:11"/>
a divine Authority in men, to whom God hath given no ſuch Authority, that we are guilty of forging Covenants in God's name, and counterfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Seals of Heaven in Ratification of them. And what can be more treaſonable by all the principles of Government? what is more provoking and more difficultly pardonable? Theſe are his words; and they are indeed ſevere and frightfull; but as one ſaith, the Devil hurts thoſe moſt he leaſt affrighteth. Our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that the old Church of <hi>England</hi> owned the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Proteſtant Churches as true Churches, and their Miniſters as true Paſtors. It is but a few (I hope) of the Innovators, that call themſelves the Church of <hi>England;</hi> that ſay, they have no true Miniſters that have not an uninterrupted Succeſſion of Dioceſan Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination from the Apoſtles. It was theſe men, or men of theſe Principles that made the ſevere Acts, that required Re-ordination; and have been the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of all the dividing, perſecuting, ſilencing Laws, to which God Almighty, by bringing in of our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant King, hath put a ſtop. I ſhall mention one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence more that they muſt neceſſarily own that go this way; if our Miniſtry without the concurrence of a Biſhop in our Ordination be a Nullity, our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations alſo in the giving the Sacraments muſt be a Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, a counterfeiting of the broad Seals of Heaven, to ſpeak in the words of the before-mention'd Author, thoſe that we baptiz'd are not indeed baptiz'd. It follows hence that our Sovereign Lord the King had need to addreſs himſelf to them for Baptiſm; for I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded he that gave his Majeſty Chriſtian Baptiſm was not Epiſcopally ordain'd. And ſurely that Prince that would be ſupreme head of the Church, had need to be initiated by Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>More might be ſaid in confirmation of this, but I ſhall ſpend the remainder of our time in drawing ſome practical Inferences from the Diſcourſe.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:133594:11"/>
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore, It appears from hence, that they that nullifie the Miniſtry of ſuch perſons, who have all that is neceſſary to prove their Miſſion, are no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Friends to the Reformation. Our firſt Reformers, though they differed from the Foreign Proteſtant Churches, acted from Catholick Principles, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the Foreign Ordinations, chuſing rather to aſſert the Identity of Biſhops and Presbyters, than to expoſe thoſe Churches that had thrown out our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Prelacy. And though they pleaded for Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they acknowledged that it was not neceſſary to the being, but only <hi>ad bene eſſe</hi> of the Church. And it was not till our Reformation went backward by an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring in a Coalition with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Reordination was required of them that had been ordained before by Presbyters. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> at <hi>Oxford, Martin Bucer</hi> at <hi>Cambridge</hi> had Eccleſiaſtical Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Church of <hi>England; Cranmer</hi> that invited them hither never required Re-ordination of them. <hi>Whittingham</hi> was made Dean of <hi>Durham</hi> though it was known, that in his Exile in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s time, he had been ordain'd by Presbyters only. Mr. <hi>Travers</hi> ordain'd by a Presbytery beyond the Sea, was ſuffered quietly to hold the place of a Centurer at the <hi>Temple.</hi> Mr. <hi>Camero</hi> ordain'd in <hi>France</hi> had the like liberty, by the Permiſſion of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, when that King was about to ſet up Epiſcopacy in <hi>Scotland;</hi> it was argued whether the Biſhops intended for <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould not be ordain'd firſt Miniſters, becauſe they had not received Ordination by a Biſhop, and it was carried in the negative by the means of Biſhop <hi>Boncroft.</hi> Thus this matter went till Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> (whoſe great deſign it was to bring about a Reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) made it his buſineſs to pleaſe the Romaniſts, and it could not but pleaſe them to ſee thoſe that had the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133594:12"/>
management of our Church affairs here in <hi>England,</hi> declare a Nullity in our Miniſtry and Miniſtrations, they knew it would be a good ſtep towards Popery. This deſign dying with him was reviv'd again upon the coming in of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. Surely thoſe learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men and Biſhops that had been with that King in his Exile beyond the Seas, muſt be ſuppoſed to know that King's Religion, and what his deſigns were; theſe were they that among other hard things that they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon us to the exerciſe of our Miniſtry, brought a neceſſity of Re-ordination.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Seeing the ſincere deſire of doing good to Souls is ſo neceſſary to prove Miniſters to be ſent of God, I beg of you that are to be ordain'd this day to look to your Aims and Ends, that they be ſuch, for Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of intention is abſolutely required to the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of what we do; ſo that though we do what is commanded, but not becauſe it is commanded; it is as if we had not done it, nay 'tis in ſome reſpect as if God had not commanded it. Remember the words of the Prophet concerning <hi>Jehu.</hi> He was command-to deſtroy the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and yet becauſe he did what he was commanded, but not with that Purity of Intention as was neceſſary to his acceptance, not to deſtroy Idolatry as he pretended, but to eſtabliſh himſelf in the Kingdom, therefore, ſaith God, <hi>I will avenge the blood of</hi> Jezreel <hi>upon the houſe of Jehu,</hi> Hoſ. 1.3, 4. The more entirely we aim at this, the doing of good, the turning men from the evil of their ways and doings, the more contented we ſhall be in our preſent circumſtances; in which, though we have not that encouragement as we could deſire, yet we have more than the Primitive Preachers of the Goſpel ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd for the ſpace of three hundred years: we have more encouragement than we expected, or indeed could rationally expect, enough therefore to make us thankfully to acknowledge <hi>it is the Lord's doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:133594:12"/>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Seeing the Gifts of Knowledge and Utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance are ſo highly neceſſary to the Miniſtry, let us more endeavour to qualifie our ſelves with thoſe Gifts that may evidence it to the People, that we are ſent of God, and not truſt to the Ceremony of Ordination, which when it is applied to men utterly deſtitute of thoſe Gifts may be a mere Nullity. A Mute or an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diot is no Miniſter though ordain'd. Our care there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould be, ours that are in the Miniſtry, and yours that ſtand as Candidates for the Miniſtry, to keep and increaſe thoſe Gifts that may enable us to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all Miniſterial Duties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> We are the mouth of the people to God. What! ſhould a Miniſter look no further to accompliſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for that part of his Miniſtry, but to read out of the Book what he hath to pray for in behalf of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? God commandeth Chriſtians <hi>to pray with all Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Supplication in the Spirit,</hi> Eph. 6.18. And is the Miniſtry exempted? ſhould he not be able to do that which every private Chriſtian is required to do? A Miniſter ſhould not be confin'd to the Fetters of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens narrow defective Words and Books, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be ſaid on behalf of ſuch as need the help of a compoſed Form, I wonder that men ſhould think it neceſſary that all ſhould be confin'd to them. It can't be ſuppoſed that all do need them. Let us not be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted out of our duty by a pretence that the thing is not attainable, on a ſudden to expreſs our deſires. Remember the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our Infirmities, for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought.</hi> The Apoſtle doth not ſay, the Book will tell you, for then there was none, for ought appears, but the Spirit helpeth our Infirmities. So that Spiritual Prayer was in the Church, before the Jeſuits brought it in. This Gift of the Spirit all ought to pray for, Miniſters eſpecially, that they may not only deſire graciouſly, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133594:13"/>
things neceſſary, but expreſs theſe deſires on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the people, that they by joyning with us may make them their own deſires. And we ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to excell in this Gift, that we may avoid all thoſe Indecencies, which thoſe that idolize Forms are apt to take notice of and expoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> a fooliſh Loquacity, pouring out (as one ſaith) tumultuous indigeſted thoughts. <hi>We are not raſhly to utter any thing before the Lord,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.2. We ſhould alſo avoid vain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, <hi>for we ſhall not be heard for much ſpeaking,</hi> Matth. 6 7. We ſhould alſo avoid affected Words and Phraſes, for certainly the more plain and familiar our words are, the better they ſuit with the nature of Prayer. In a word, we ſhould endeavour to obſerve the general rule of our Saviour, <hi>not to be as the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</hi> Thus let us all endeavour to accompliſh our ſelves for this part of our Miniſtry; and if our Brethren out of a fondneſs to their own way of Devotion will ridicule our Performances, and expoſe us to their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, let us patiently bear it, 'tis no new thing for men to pretend that there are Barbariſms and Soleciſms in the Prayers of Miniſters. This St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> takes notice of in his time. <hi>Ita enim non irredebunt, ſe aliquos auteſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; miniſtros eccleſiae forte animadveniunt, vel cum barbariſmis &amp; ſoleciſmis deum invocare.</hi> So they will not jeer, if perhaps they take notice, that ſome Biſhops and Miniſters of the Church do invocate God with Barbariſms and Soleciſms: to ſuch as feared this, he ſaith, God mindeth not ſo much the Expreſſion, as the inward Affection. This paſſage by the way proves that ſuch Prayers were then uſed, in which ſome might pretend there were Barbariſms. Surely they could not be Forms preſcribed by the Church. However if we meet with the ſame uſage, the ſame Language that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his time obſerv'd, let us not wonder at it; it ſeems it is no new thing, and therefore we ſhould the more patiently bear it, and watch our own Spirits,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133594:13"/>
that we do not expoſe and make their way of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worſe than it is, becauſe they expoſe ours. For the Spirit of Prayer and true Devotion may be in thoſe that confine themſelves to a Form. And they that uſe no Forms may be as formal as other Men. There is (as one ſaith, and I think he ſaith well in it) a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Guſt as to Spiritual things, that may differ as much as men do as to Meat and Drink. In which one liketh and is nouriſhed by that which another loatheth, and it may be would do him hurt, if it were impos'd upon him. I do believe that the true Spirit of Prayer may be in thoſe that do not well relliſh our way, and they ought (and I doubt not but many of them do) think ſo of ours. Let every one have what he liketh, and let no man be drench'd with what he loatheth. It is but a few of that way, and they (I doubt) none of the moſt devout Perſons, that will dare to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any, but eſpecially upon ſuch frivolous pretences, Chriſtians have more need to be rebuk'd for the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Prayer in Secret and in their Families, than for praying without or with a Form. However it ſhould quiet us to conſider, that if the Controverſie be (as for ought we know it is) who ſhall do beſt, it is the more pardonable, provided it be done on both ſides, with that Reverence and Unweariedneſs as it ought to be done, but woe be to that Hypocrite that ſhall be found in the Omiſſion of that great Duty, for which he was ſuch a Stickler. <hi>They eat up my people, as they eat Bread, and call not upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> Pſalm 14.8. To conclude this particular, it doth ſeem to me, whatever is pretended to the contrary, that our firſt Reformers who compoſed the Liturgy, were far enough from the mind of thoſe that plead for its Impoſition; they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd thoſe Forms to aſſiſt Miniſters, that coming new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of Popery muſt be ſuppos'd to need thoſe helps, not with an intent to exclude and run down <hi>extempore,</hi> conceiv'd Prayer. There is one paſſage in the Office
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133594:14"/>
of Ordination, that makes me think ſo; it is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the Sponſions, and in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> After this the Congregation ſhall be deſir'd ſecretly in their Prayers to make their humble Supplications to God for all theſe things, for the which Prayers, there ſhall be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence kept for a ſpace. By this paſſage it appears that the Compilers of our Liturgy, as being ſenſible of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of a Form of Words, thought it neceſſary to give the Congregation a ſpace of time, that every perſon might abound in his own way of conceived Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Being we are to ſpeak from God to the people, in which reſpect a Miniſter is as God's Mouth to declare the whole counſel of God to them; we ſhould endeavour to accompliſh our ſelves for this work, that we may do this according to the direction that St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives <hi>Titus, chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 8. <hi>With ſoundneſs of Doctrine, and with Speech that cannot be blam'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us endeavour to do it with Soundneſs of Doctrine, <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Speak thou the things which become ſound Doctrine:</hi> Now to do this there is need of skill, the Chriſtian Religion is baited with many Controverſies, and that in ſome material points. The Enemy hath ſown his Tares, Books that ſtrike at all reveal'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are in all parts of the Nation; Miniſters whoſe Calling it is to look into Books, ſhould be able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, that they may do their part to prevent the ſpreading of thoſe opinions, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf, and to thy Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, Soundneſs of Speech that cannot be blam'd,</hi> v. 8. That not only the matter we deliver be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Analogy of Faith, but we ſhould be able to expreſs our Thoughts ſo as that the wording of our matter be not deſpis'd. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue is much refin'd of late years. I confeſs we ſhould avoid on the one hand quaintneſs of Speech, that which the Apoſtle calls <hi>the words of man's wiſdom,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.4. In the uſe of this it is poſſible for thoſe that affect a florid
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133594:14"/>
Stile, to preach to the people to as little purpoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, as if we preach'd in another Language; he no doubt is the beſt Preacher, that can make every thing that he preacheth to the people, eaſie to be underſtood. And yet we ſhould take heed of falling into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme this way, and fill mens ears with an empty Sound of Words, nauſeous Repetitions, and for want of Matter, ſay over and over the ſame thing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver words without Matter.</p>
               <p>Having gotten theſe Gifts, let us ſee to it, that we don't loſe them. The way to have the continuance and increaſe of theſe, is to uſe them to the end for which they are given. The way to pray better is to pray more, the way to preach better is to preach more. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one learneth by teaching, and gets at leaſt a more orderly digeſted knowledge. Let every one do his beſt, and ſtir up the Gift that is in him, and by this means he will attain to do better, and his profiting will appear. God threathens the <hi>Idol-ſhepherds, that their arm ſhould be dried, and their right eye darkned,</hi> Zech. 11.17. This is a Judgment to be feared by all men, Miniſters eſpecially, even the darkning, wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Operations of God's Spirit.</p>
               <p>In a word, we ſhould endeavour in a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to accompliſh our ſelves for occaſional Diſcourſes, I confeſs 'tis more natural for ſome men, all have not a preſence of Mind and Thought, nor a command of words to expreſs their own thoughts, and yet 'tis that which Miniſters eſpecially ſhould endeavour after, that upon all occaſions we may be able to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon ſuited to the occaſion.</p>
               <p>I could not but take particular notice of what I lately met with in a Book written by a Jeſuit, one of the Miſſionaries that the <hi>French</hi> King employed in that great Empire of <hi>China,</hi> to convert them to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in thoſe parts: He obſerves that he found more good done by thoſe occaſional Diſcourſes, than by his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133594:15"/>
ſtudied Performances; People were more affected and wrought upon by what was ſaid to them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular concerning a future State, the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than of what he had ſaid with more ſtrength of reaſon in the Congregation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let us then deliver and look after the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that Meſſage that God hath ſent by us; a faithfull Meſſenger ought to deliver the whole Meſſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> let us deliver our Meſſage with all faithfulneſs, and without Partiality, and reſpect of perſons. Say to the wicked, it ſhall go ill with him; ſay to the righteous it ſhall go well with him. Have we a care of mincing the matter; <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I command you.</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour as ſent of God kept within the bounds of his Commiſſion, <hi>John</hi> 12.49. <hi>I have not ſpoken of my ſelf, but the Father which hath ſent me, he hath given Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, what I ſhall ſay, and what I ſhould ſpeak.</hi> And therefore ſurely Miniſters ſhould take heed, that we may be able to ſay with our Saviour, <hi>my Doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> And yet we ſhould not only deliver, but look after the ſucceſs of our Meſſage, and to take care to do every thing, that may promote and not hinder the ſucceſs of our Miniſtry, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.28 <hi>Warning eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and teaching every man in all wiſdom, that we may preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And this we ſhould endeavour,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> By a Life ſuitable to our Calling. Surely our Relation to God, as ſent by him, doth oblige us to take heed of our ſelves, that our Miniſtry be not blamed, for if we do not live well, not only we in our Perſons, <hi>but our Miniſtry will be blam'd,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.3. 'Tis true it ſhould not be ſo, why ſhould the Miniſtry be blam'd for the faults of ſome men? And yet becauſe men will do it, therefore we ſhould take the more heed to our ways. The people ſhould not have abhorr'd the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133594:15"/>
Lord's Offerings, becauſe <hi>Eli</hi>'s Sons were wicked lewd men, and yet it was an Aggravation of their Sin, that they gave the people that occaſion. The Apoſtle ſaith to <hi>Timothy, let no man deſpiſe thy youth,</hi> 1 Tim, 4.12. He doth not ſay it to the people, becauſe generally when we are deſpis'd, the fault is in our ſelves; and the way to prevent, that the people may not deſpiſe ſuch of us as are young, or upon any other account, is to do what the Apoſtle there exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to, <hi>Be thou an example to believers, in word, in converſation, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity.</hi> The greateſt Gifts of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will never do that good, as their bad example will do hurt. The people not only that are ignorant but ſuch as fear God, will take bad Impreſſions, and many times will be led away by the example of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, eſpecially in things that are diſputable, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle obſerves that many were carried away by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation of <hi>Peter;</hi> ſo that he was conſtrained to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him openly before the Church,</hi> Gal. 2.14. In a word, we ſhould be the more carefull to give in all things a good example, for they that ſcruple to hear us, will be quick-ſighted to obſerve what is amiſs in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ſhould not only deliver but endeavour the ſucceſs of our Meſſage from God to the people by our inceſſant Prayers; for 'tis Prayer that renders our endeavours in the Miniſtry fruitfull and ſucceſsfull. Paul <hi>may plant, and</hi> Apollos <hi>may water, but 'tis God that muſt give the increaſe.</hi> Let a Miniſter be never ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and convincing in his Diſcourſes, all his labour will be fruitleſs without divine Grace ſucceeding it. A Key that is exactly fit to all the Wards of the Lock, cannot open it without an hand to turn it. Let the moſt proper and powerfull motives to work upon the heart be repreſented in the proper light, and evidence to the utmoſt advantage; they cannot open the heart, this is God's work, and this we ſhould pray for. It is obſervable, that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant would not deliver
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133594:16"/>
the Meſſage for which he was ſent, till he had firſt prayed to God to ſucceed it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.12. And then juſt as he prayed ſo it fell out. Thus when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was to make his Requeſt to the King, he darted up a ſhort Prayer to the God of Heaven, before he would ſpeak to the King, <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.5, 6. <hi>For what doſt thou make thy requeſt? So I prayed to the God of Heaven, and ſaid to the King, Let us do the like.</hi> The Goſpel is the power of God to Salvation, but ſtill Prayer is requiſite to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the holy Spirit, by whoſe influence the word proves effectual. What is more worthy of our conſtant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers than precious immortal Souls? I do remember what I read in the Life of that moſt eminent Man of God, Mr. <hi>Walſh</hi> a Miniſter of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who being to preach in the Afternoon, he tarried ſo long at his houſe, that the Congregation thought fit to ſend the Clerk to ſee what the matter was that Mr. <hi>Walſh</hi> ſtaid beyond his uſual time; the Clerk drawing near the room where he was, heard a very loud Voice, and ſtanding ſtill, he heard him with great importunity, oft repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe words of <hi>Moſes</hi> to God, <hi>If thy preſence go not with me, I will not go from hence;</hi> as if he had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not to preach till God ſhould hear his Prayers for the ſucceſs. Accordingly it fell out, he had never that ſucceſs as at that time, and yet none had greater at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> As for you the people that are aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether upon this occaſion, I have a word or two to ſpeak, and I have done. If Miniſters thus diſpos'd and qualified, thus approv'd of and inveſted in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, are ſent of God, your duty is to own them and receive them as ſuch. Pray conſider two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Who it is that hath ſent them. We Miniſters are in all other reſpects as you are, but we are in God's ſtead, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>We pray you in Chriſt's ſtead be ye recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God.</hi> God in this matter dealeth wiſely in dealing familiarly with you, he doth not ſpeak immediately to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133594:16"/>
you from Heaven, that the terrors of his Majeſty may not make you afraid, but ſendeth men, men of like Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with our ſelves, who, if they deceive you, they muſt deceive their own Souls. Take heed therefore of deſpiſing the methods of the Almighty, that it is by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching, or that it is by men that the Meſſage of the Almighty is brought unto you. In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters the Meſſenger is received according to the reſpect we have to him that ſent him. Our Saviour doth much inſiſt upon this, that he came not in his own name, but in the name of him that ſent him. And he tells his Diſciples, <hi>as the Father ſent me into the world, ſo I ſend you,</hi> abating only for what is extraordinary; as Chriſt ſent the firſt Apoſtles, ſo he ſends the ordinary Miniſters of the Goſpel; <hi>lo I am with you to the end of the world; with you as long as you ſhall live, and with them that ſhall ſucceed you in the ordinary work of the Miniſtry.</hi> The Apoſtles were ſent with extraordinary Gifts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with an infallible Spirit, to write Scriptures, with Gifts of Miracles, Gifts of Tongues; but for the main, the ſubſtance of the Commiſſion is the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Grace of God to every man, and to reveal the Will of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider the Meſſage that Miniſters bring you. God and man were at variance, the Son of God hath done and ſuffered all that was neceſſary on his part to make peace; Miniſters are ſent in the ſtead of Chriſt to perſwade men to accept of thoſe terms, upon which peace may be had. Behold we come as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Servant, to propoſe a Match between the Son of God, and the Sons of men, to eſpouſe you to Chriſt. God hath ſent us to invite you, nay to compell you to come to the Marriage-Feaſt, and to tell you that all things are ready on God's part. We can ſhew you, as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.22. the Bracelets and the Ear-rings, and the precious things that God hath ſent you by us. I don't ſpeak this to gain outward
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133594:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Reſpect and Precedence before men, but you are to conſider, that whatever reſpect you ſhow Miniſters, 'tis infinitely ſhort of what is due to them, till the Meſſage they bring you be entertain'd. To receive us and entertain us as one Friend doth another at your Table, alas what is this? To receive a Prophet in the name of a Prophet is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Meſſage he brings you. We are ſent to perſwade you to be reconcil'd to God; your kindneſs to us is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, till you are become the Friends of God that ſent us. When <hi>Ehud</hi> told <hi>Eglon</hi> that he had a Meſſage from God to him, <hi>he aroſe out of his ſeat,</hi> Judg. 3.20. Our Meſſage is not as his was, but 'tis a Meſſage of Peace and good-will. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore, whatever the Meſſenger is, the Meſſage is weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And whatever oppoſition we may meet with from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others, that condemn us and our Preaching as ſchiſmatical, our Miniſtry as a Nullity; though they accuſe us for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting the great Seals of Heaven, if we can prevail in our Meſſage, which is to perſwade you to be reconcil'd to God, to eſpouſe you to Chriſt; 'tis this will ſupport us under all the hard Speeches of men otherwiſe minded. Now it lieth upon you to enable us, to uſe the words of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> among whom there were ſome of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that did not only deſpiſe his Perſon and Gifts, but did alſo queſtion his Apoſtleſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. <hi>If I be not an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to others, yet doubtleſs I am to you; for the Seal of mine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip are ye in the Lord.</hi> See you to it that you diſprove them that nullifie our Miniſtry. Perhaps you are not able to anſwer all the Objections that may be made againſt our Miniſtry, and Preaching: No more was the blind man in the Goſpel able to anſwer all that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid againſt Chriſt; but he had an inartificial Argument drawn from the good he had receiv'd from him, that put them all to ſilence. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I was born blind, now I ſee.</hi> Saith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forget thy precepts, for by them thou haſt quickned me.</hi> Whilſt others expoſe our Prayers as nonſenſical, or worſe, if by this Mode of Praying, in which we lead you to the Throne of Grace, you keep up the Spirit of Devotion; if by our Miniſtry we perſwade you to be reconcil'd to God, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſe you to Chriſt; if our Miniſtry obtain its great end upon you, which is to better Mankind; by this means we ſhall be encouraged, and you ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
